A Guide to the Papers of Theodore Dreiser 1898-1945
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Theodore Dreiser, 1898-1945
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
6220
This collection consists of 350 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was given to the Library by Clifton Waller Barrett on January 30, 1960.
Scope and Content Information
The collection contains 83 manuscripts of works by Dreiser including his novel Jennie Gerhardt; short essays, chiefly biographical sketches; poems; stories; interviews; miscellaneous pieces; and galley proofs of An American Tragedy.
Essay topics include William Archer, Philip Armour, Katherine Bloodgood, John Burroughs, Joseph H. Choate, H. Barringer Cox, Louise Cox, Edward Croarkin, Chauncey Depew, William De Morgan, Frank E. Elwell, Louis Fagan, Frank Fowler, Gilbert Gane, Frank Wakely Gunsaulus, Moses Handy, William Dean Howells, John LaFarage, Henry Wadsworth Longfellow, Lillian Nordica, Horace Pingree, Maria Louise Pool, George M. Pullman, Thomas B. Reed, Bayard Taylor, the University of Chicago, J. Q. A. Ward, modern business men, the University of Chicago, The American Museum of Natural History, Armour Institute, American women composers, artists, dramatists, and poets, Brandywine, Cedermere, Cramp Ship Yards, and lynching.
Correspondence discusses his writing, publication efforts, critical reaction, censorship, legal suits with publishers, (John Lane Company) and his personal life including friendships, romances and travel.
Specific topics include early editorial work, the publication of Sister Carrie, The Titan, and The Genius in an era of censorship; suppression of "The Genius"; copyright problems; a possible dramatization of Sister Carrie; a French translation and a film version of "An American Tragedy"; a hiking trip from Georgia to New Jersey; African-Americans in Savannah; Walt Whitman and Mark Twain; religious views; role of the Author's League of America; dislike of film version of An American Tragedy; Norman Duncan; the Fortean Society; respect for Lenin and Trotsky; Caldwell's Tobacco Road.
Miscellaneous material includes the Anti-Vice Commission report on The Genius; promotional pamphlets; and clippings pertaining to Dreiser.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged chronologically.
Contents List
- Manuscripts
  - "A Decorative Painter of the American School" n.d., AMs, 20 p.
    Essay regarding Frank Fowler.
  - "Are Thou a Mourner" n.d., AMsS, 1 p., in bound volume
    Poem; 6 3-line verses
  - "A Famous English Savant" n.d., Ms, 7 p.
    Essay regarding Louis Fagan, Director of British museum, to lecture in America.
  - "The Homes of Longfellow" n.d., AMsS, 31 p.
    Essay's literary criticism; character sketch, including some verses.
  - Little Essays on Great Problems: "The Bubble of Success" n.d., AMsS, 13 p.
    Essay
  - "Lying About Success" n.d., AMsS, 8 p.
  - "The Paintings of William Morgan" n.d., AMsS, 15 p.
    Essay, includes typed copy, 7 p.
  - "Moses P. Handy" [of Chicago] n.d., AMs, 4 p.
  - "On Neutral Men" n.d., AMsS, 4 p.
  - "The Philosophy of the Minor Note" n.d., AMsS, 33 p.
  - "The Prize Winners of the National Academy" n.d., AMsS, 14 p.
  - "Pullman" n.d., Ms, 33 p.
    Essay regarding the company, the town, and the man.
  - "Reforming the World" n.d., AMsS, 8 p.
  - "The Rise of the Plaster Image" n.d., AMsS, 8 p.
  - "The Supremacy of the Modern Businessman" n.d., AMsS, 9 p.
  - "In the Haunts of Bay and Taylor" n.d., AMsS, 33 p.
  - "The University of Chicago" n.d., AMsS, 33 p.
  - "A Victim of Justice" n.d., Ms, 23 p.
    Story regarding a lynching
  - "J. Q. A. Ward" n.d., AMsS, 18 p.
    Essay regarding a sculptor; 7 1/2 pages in Theodore Dreiser's hand; 10 1/2 pages in Mrs. Dreiser's hand
  - "J. Q. A. Ward" n.d., AMsS, 38 p.
  - "What the New Century Offers the Young Men" n.d., AMsS, 25 p.
    Essay regarding a conversation with Chauncey M. Depew
  - "A Woman Painter of Cattle" n.d., AMsS, 4 p., includes typescript, 5 p.
    Essay regarding painter Matilda Browne
  - Review of A Golden Sorrow, by Mary Louise Poole n.d., AMsS, 3 p., includes typescript, 2 p.
    Book review by Poole, a poet
  - Interview with Marshall Field n.d., AMs, 6 p.
    Typed questions with autograph responses.
  - Interview with Dr. Frank Wakely Gunsaulus and [Marshall] Field n.d., AMs, 4 p.
    Outline of questions; includes 2 p. of poetry, crossed out on verso
  - "Interview with Lillian Nordica" n.d., AMsS, 21 p.
    Incomplete interview of musician and opera star.
  - Interview of Governor Horace V. Pingree of Michigan n.d., AMsS, 30 p.
  - "Interview with Tom Reed" n.d., AMsS, 26 p.
    A study of Thomas Brockett Reed, Speaker of the House, in his Maine home.
  - Notes for biographical sketch of [Frank Edwin] Elwell n.d., AMs, 2 p.
  - Notes for biographical sketch of Gilbert Gane n.d., AMs, 3 p.
  - Notes on [William Dean] Howells n.d., AMs, 1 p.
  - Notes painter [John] Lafarge n.d., AMs, 3 p.
  - Notes on painter William Morgan n.d., AMs, 4 p.
  - Autobiographical attack on Grant Richards ca. 1911, AMs, 22 p.
    Essay; includes 2 p. copy addressed to Grant Richard's secretary; attacks Grant Richards who persuaded Theodore Dreiser to stop writing it before it was completed; regards publication of Sister Carrie in 1900; states that he earned $1500 a year editing 7 magazines; resigns to resume work on Jennie Gerhardt; Richards offers to publish Dreiser's books in England; reflect on life, future, his standing as an artist.
  - Essay [1924], TsS, 12 p., includes ms corrections; includes carbon typescript, 9 p. with corrections
    Regards a literary luncheon with John Cowonos
  - "A Decorative Painter of the American School" n.d., TsS, 10 p.
    Essay regarding Frank Fowler
  - A Hoosier Holiday n.d., Ts, 1 p.
    First page of book, includes ms corrections
  - "The Phantom Drunkard" n.d., Ts, 19 p.
    Short story, includes ms corrections
  - "With the Undercurrent" n.d., TsS, 3 p.
    Essay regarding strike in New York City's garment district and the poor people who work there; includes ms corrections
  - Jennie Gerhardt n.d., Ts, 720 p. (carbon); uncut typewritten copy in 4 folders
    Novel with ms corrections, includes label from H. L. Mencken to Theodore Dreiser
  - "Brandywine, the Picturesque, After 120 Years" n.d., *AMsS, 30 p.
    Essay regarding a revoluntionary battle
  - "The Brandywine After 120 Years" n.d., *AMsS, 4 p.
    Essay regarding the river and area of a revolutionary battle.
- Letters
  - Theodore Dreiser to Duffy 1898 Aug 24, ALS, 1 p.
    Hopes he will like the poem; writes that it could be illustrated; wishes Duffy would look at Dreiser's poem in the September Success; wants his signature.
  - Theodore Dreiser to Duffy 1905 Mar 21, TLS, 1 p.
    Needs humorous jokes for new magazine, Smith's, published by the publishers of Ainslee's; offers usual rate for submissions.
  - Theodore Dreiser to [Edna] Kenton 1905 May 6, ALS, 4 p.
    Thanks for her kind words; writes that Sister Carrie is still in the doldrums, though the general situation is better; mentions that book is well known; owns plates and hopes to find publisher for them; thinks he met her in 1892 in Chicago while peddling books; calls himself older and wiser, but no less radical, simply sorrowful and uncertain.
  - Theodore Dreiser to Sidney Portier 1907 Dec 31, TLS, 1 p. w/env.
    Writes that 3 weeks before seeing his stories has turned into 3 months and that it is time he had a look at the first of them.
  - Theodore Dreiser to [William] C. Lengel 1911 Oct 15, ALS, 6 p.
    Writes in "A Letter About Himself," that Harper has 2 books of his letters and clippings and he has more letters from critics and editor; mentions he is in Who's Who, his favorite book, his characteristics, his books issued and those suppressed, and his wish to be rich.
  - Theodore Dreiser to [Franklin P.] Adams 1911 Oct 30, ALS, 2 p.
    Thanks him for his kind words; remembers his sincere approval of Sister Carrie and Jennie Gerhardt
  - Theodore Dreiser, S. S. Mauretania to Edna Kenton 1911 Nov 22, ALS, 1 p.
    Writes that her faith and kind words will never be forgotten.
  - Theodore Dreiser to [Pauline] Hemmerde 1911 Dec 30, ANS, 1 p.
    Thanks her for post-impressionist book and the Boredecker; waives Songs of the North until her returns from Italy, since all he can do now is stick it in his trunk; writes it will be safe with the publisher.
  - Theodore Dreiser, London, to Pauline Hemmerde 1912 Jan 9, Postcard, 1 p.
    Asks her to buy a box of the same cigarettes she bought at Christmas to give to [Grant] Richards and charge them to his account.
  - Theodore Dreiser, New York, to Rider 1912 Nov 7, ALS, 2 p.
    Mails him The Financier, writes that he does not expect him to read it, rather it is for his autograph shelf.
  - Theodore Dreiser, New York, to Charles V. E. Starrett 1913 Jun 12, ALS, 4 p.
    Includes typescript and carbon typescript copeis; thanks him and Press Writer's Club for letter requesting advice and cheer; discusses qualities of new great writers at length; quotes Sidney Lanier.
  - Theodore Dreiser, New York, to [Albert] Mordell 1913 Sep 25, ALS, 4 p.
    Expresses pleasure at receiving his letter; writes that Mordell's book made a deep impression on many; welcomes a critical intellect; finds himself to have few literary prejudices, though not many literary favorites; hopes to discuss The Financier, volume one of A Triology of Desire; writes that The Titan and The Stoic will be volumes 2 and 3; expressed pleasure that Mordell likes Jennie Gerhardt as most critics perfer Sister Carrie; mentions William Marion Reedy and Thomas B. Mosten, Smart Set, The Century, A Traveller at 40; plans to publish The Titan in Harper's.
  - Theodore Dreiser, New York, to Albert Mordell, Philadelphia 1913 Oct 21, ALS, 1 p., w/env.
    Inquires about the law and the profits of book; feels pressured to complete The Titan; mentions Strindberg interview.
  - Theodore Dreiser, New York, to Albert Mordell, Philadelphia 1913 Nov 5, ALS, 4 p., w/env.
    Expresses pleasure with the opinion of his lawyer friend; feels time will justify him for The Financier and 2 succeeding volumes.
  - Theodore Dreiser, New York, to Albert Mordell, Phliadelphia 1913 Nov 5, ALS, 4 p., w/ env.
    Asks Mordell to call him or write; gives address as 23 W. 58 St.
  - Theodore Dreiser, New York, to Albert Mordell, Philadelphia 1913 Dec 1, ALS, 1 p., w/ env.
    Thanks him for galleys; calls article intelligent; complains of misrepresentation in The Sun and The Times; decides not to be interviewed any more as he is tired of literary mush; call New York papers the worst.
  - Theodore Dreiser to Albert Mordell 1913 Dec 4, ALS, 1 p., w/ env.
    Asks him to get 10 copies of an interview when it appears; calls the interview intelligent and would like to keep it for future reference.
  - Theodore Dreiser to Albert Mordell 1913 Dec 9, ALS, 1 p., w/env.
    Thanks him for review and interview; asks him to send 8-9 copies of interview.
  - Theodore Dreiser to Albert Mordell 1914 Feb 18, ALS, 2 p., w/env.
    Thanks him for clipping; intends to send copy of The Titan when it comes out.
  - Theodore Dreiser, Chicago, to Albert Mordell, Philadelphia 1914 Mar 6, ALS, 1 p., w/env.
    Writes that Harper's has decided not to publish The Titan after printing 10,000 copies; plans to issue book through one of several firms; calls it Sister Carrie all over again.
  - H. L. Mencken, Baltimore, to Theodore Dreiser, New York [1914] Mar 23, TS, 2 p. (copy)
    Writes that he has completed The Titan; calls it the best thing he has ever done with the exception of Jennie Gerhardt, which had more emotional appeal; mentions A Traveller at 40, Baltimore Sun, and the Century Co.
  - Theodore Dreiser, New York, to Mr. Rethy, Philadelphia 1914 Apr 18, ALS, 2 p.
    Comments that he has nothing to add to former letter; mentions The International and The Manes; likes Rethy's poem.
  - Theodore Dreiser to Albert Mordell 1914 May 4, ALS, 1 p., w/env.
    Thanks him for books; expects to receive books from Lane this week; intends to send one to Mordell.
  - Theodore Dreiser to Albert Mordell 1914 Jun 9, ALS, 1 p., w/env.
    Thanks him for his services in connection with Brandes, wishes he would read enclosed statement in regard to condition brought about by Mitchell Kennedy regarding John Lane and himself; believes statement illuminates American publishers publishing methods.
  - Theodore Dreiser to Albert Mordell 1914 Jun 22, ALS, 1 p., w/env.
    Writes that he is not troubled by wrathful reviews; believes that neither praise nor blame settle the fate of anything for more than a little while; encloses review, which he finds amusing.
  - Theodore Dreiser to Albert Mordell 1914 Dec 24, ALS, 2 p., w/env.
    Expresses interest in points made in lecture; presumes Mordell wrote clipping in Philadelphia Record which H. L. Mencken sent to him; asks for copies of page on which it appears; mentions speaking engagement.
  - Theodore Dreiser to Albert Mordell 1914 Dec 26, ALS, 1 p., w/env.
    Requests copies of Record to be sent to Malden in Hudson, New York
  - Theodore Dreiser, New York, to Albert Mordell, Philadelphia 1915 Jan 14, ALS, 2 p., w/env.
    Thanks him for clippings; mentions [John Cowper Powys], and a lecture he will present in Chicago
  - Theodore Dreiser to Albert Mordell 1915 Apr 28, ALS, 1 p., w/env.
    Likes all really bitter attacks, particularly one in Saturday Review; writes, "A vulgar, blatant scream" is not so bad; mentions the 50 reviews he has from England, some of which are very negative.
  - Theodore Dreiser to Albert Mordell 1915 May 6, ALS, 1 p., w/env.
    Writes The Genius will not be out until August and he will see that he gets a copy.
  - Theodore Dreiser to Albert Mordell 1915 May 13, ALS, 1 p., w/env.
    Owns rights to Sister Carrie; asks him to act as his attorney in the matter; intends to ask Hayer what is expected for Jennie Gerhardt, which is a similar case.
  - Theodore Dreiser to Albert Mordell 1915 May 12, ALS, 3 p., w/env.
    Believes paying $75 for an offense of this kind is to invite copyright stealing; writes that nothing of the kind will be done and that Harper's will proceed unless favorable adjustment is reached; mentions The Jewish World, fee to Mordell.
  - Theodore Dreiser to Albert Mordell 1915 May 19, ALS, 3 p., w/env.
    Resents change of name as he owns copyright and plates, states that if a $60,000 loss can be afforded, $500 ought not to bother them; mentions Harper's ownership of right to present selling edition.
  - Theodore Dreiser to Albert Mordell 1915 Sep 24, ALS, 1 p., w/env.
    Sends bill
  - Theodore Dreiser to Albert Mordell 1915 Oct 31, ALS, 1 p., w/env.
    Discusses The Genius; mentions New York Globe; thinks he is entitled to indicate thoughts of characters in their own language.
  - Theodore Dreiser to Albert Mordell 1915 Nov 28, ALS, 2 p., w/env.
    Believes he will assume art and literary direction of a large film corporation; opens himself to suggestions concerning plays, books, legends, etc., that could be scenarios; seeks subject of distinction, true drama, and poignance; promises to reward Mordell for any ideas of value.
  - Theodore Dreiser to Albert Mordell 1915 Nov 30, ALS, 1 p., w/env.
    Asks for a few preliminary suggestions so Dreiser may catch the drift of his mind and taste.
  - Theodore Dreiser to Albert Mordell 1916 Jan 19, ALS, 2 p., w/env.
    Thanks him for Ms. Skidelsky's review; states that she is all wrong about The Titan; calls it the best book he has ever done; mentions H. L. Mencken, trip to Savannah; requests guess of how many copies of The Genius have been sold in Philadelphia.
  - Theodore Dreiser to Little 1916 Jan 28, Typescript copy
    Discusses review of Maughan's Of Human Bondage; sends thanks; asserts that they are blessed to be able to enthuse over anything openly.
  - Theodore Dreiser, Savannah, Georgia, to Willard Dillman, Minneapolis 1916 Feb 7, ALS, 4 p., w/env.
    Complains of grippe, which has caused him to leave New York; undertakes unpleasantly large business; finds Dillman's letter sincere and entertainingly philosophic; comments that people who think logically and incisively are rare; marvels at how cleverly the world is run based on tradition and precept; writes that he does not know if the world is getting better or worse; comments that the world improves mechanically and is virtually static and that love is not rewarded nor hate punished; comments on himself, psuedo intellectuals, and laborers; hopes to see him sometime in Savannah.
  - Theodore Dreiser, Savannah, to Willard Dillmann, Minneapolis 1916 Mar 9, ALS, 4 p., w/env.
    Puts friendship and affection before anything else; welcomes him as a friend; leans to anyone who approaches him via regard; mentions Savannah's Black population; calls them respectful, docile, and clean, which is more than he can say of the poor of other races; wishes for him to get a copy of Plays of the Natural and Supernatural and tell Dresier what he thinks of it.
  - Theodore Dreiser, New York, to Mayan [Little] 1916 Jun 21, ALS, 1 p.
    Requests that first chapter be sent without waiting to finish all 3 copies of remaining chapters; needs to get them to H. L. Mencken at the earliest date; wishes he would write John Cowper Powys and suggest "Cowperwood" is legitimately spelled "Cooperwood."
  - Theodore Dreiser, New York, to Willard Dillman 1916 Jul 31, ALS, 4 p.
    Expresses pleasure at receiving Dillman's letter regarding Dreiser's plays, not because he agreed, but because he was forthright; fancies he should stick to novels, despite his former intentions to write a few 3 or 4 act plays; works hard, but not always in New York; considers going on a trip from Denver west with a friend and will stop off in Minneapolis if he does; cheers the Anti-Vice Society for suppressing The Genius, which is already done save for prosecution, which will occur if any more copies are sold; states that John Lane Co. will fight, but may already be beaten by the Puritan courts; asserts that his work will be viewed with care from now on.
  - Theodore Dreiser, New York, to Mayan [Little] 1916 Aug 1, ALS, 1 p.
    Expresses gratitude for copies of vice charges; wishes he would spread news of suppression of The Genius as widely as possible; want to put Lane Co. where they will have to fight, whether they want to or not.
  - Theodore Dreiser, New York, to Albert Mordell, Philadelphia 1916 Dec 13, ALS, 3 p., w/env.
    Approves interview if he lets Dreiser go over the manuscript proofs beforehand; states that his corrections are seldom heeded when corrects only proofs.
  - Theodore Dreiser, New York, To Willard Dillman, Minneapolis 1917 Jan 11, ALS, 3 p., w/env.
    Expresses pleasure that Dillman likes A Hoosier Holiday; finds comment about his return to Catholicism amusing; denies idea that Catholics return to Catholicism; states that his present faculties will have to change if he is to return to Catholicism on his deathbed as it is claimed Voltaire did.
  - Theodore Dreiser, New York, to Albert Mordell 1917 Apr 4, ALS, 1 p., w/env.
    Explains that he and Lane Co. are not on the best terms at present, but they may claim Dreiser advised them to send document which Dreiser has not had time to read over.
  - Theodore Dreiser, New York, to Albert Mordell, Philadelphia 1917 Aug 22, ALS, 3 p., w/env.
    Discusses case regarding The Genius, which is before the Appellate Division of the Supreme Court; states that his counsel, Standfield & Levy, have a brief on his behalf and John Lane Co., whom he is suing to compel them to fulfill contract and publish The Genius, have filed a brief in reply; writes that Joseph S. Auerbach has been called into the case by Standfield & Levy to argue the case after October 1; sends brief.
  - Theodore Dreiser, New York, to Albert Mordell, Philadelphia 1917 Sep 11, ALS, 2 p., w/env.
    Like article, but does not think he should publish everything he learns in private; requests 20 copies of papers in question, as the lawyers can use them.
  - Edward H. Smith of Monday World, New York, to Theodore Dreiser 1918 Feb 24, Typescript copy
    Suggests a banquet for him the evening after the decision in The Genius case is handed down; lists possible guests; requests Dreiser's consent; offers alternative of dinner for American Literary that Liberalism with Dreiser as guest of honor; suggests publicity idea for The Genius involving K. K. Kitchen, Puritanism, Comstockism, and Anti-Puritanic ideas; suggests that Dreiser communicate with his lawyers and publishers.
  - Theodore Dreiser, New York, to Willard Dillman, Minneapolis 1918 Apr 23, ALS, 3 p., w/env.
    Believes Lavinsky(?) is a good piece of realism and wishes he might write 6 books like it; intends to join Willard on trip to New Orleans and towards the gulf; mentions his 1910 separation from his wife; wants to figure out expenses so they can split costs; thinks September would be the perfect time to begin traveling.
  - Theodore Dreiser, New York, to [Frank] Harris 1918 May 11, ALS, 2 p.
    Writes that he will meet him anytime; suggests he come to dinner at a quiet spot.
  - Theodore Dreiser, Havre de Grace, Maryland, to Willard Dillman, Minneapolis 1918 May 30, ALS, 4 p.
    Writes that he has been in the woods eating and working and the air makes him sleepy; plans to work in the city, as he requires typing services there; expresses interest in Mississippi trip; plans to take Dillman up on offer to visit "Excelsior."
  - Theodore Dreiser, New York, to [Frank] Harris 1918 Jun 5, ALS, 1 p.
    Encloses manuscript of an essay disguised as a posthumous autobiography; wants his opinion; believes the manuscript too different for any American publisher.
  - Theodore Dreiser, Havre de Grace, Maryland to [Frank Harris] 1918 Jun 7, ALS, 1 p., w/ postcard to Dreiser
    Sends sketch; mentions that he has been complimented on his speaking ability; includes advertising card for "Theodore Dreiser: America's Greatest Novelist," a lecture by Andre Tredon.
  - Theodore Dreiser, Havre de Grace, Maryland, to [Frank] Harris 1918 Jun 17, ALS, 3 p.
    Hopes to write out Sister Carrie incident and points in connection with his philosophy; explains that Hey, Rub-a-Dub should not be assumed to represent his mental state; mentions 1911-1912 visit to Europe, which he recorded in A Traveller at 40; discusses Whitman, Twain, Huckleberry Finn, Tom Sawyer
  - Theodore Dreiser, New York, to [Frank] Harris 1918 Jul 5, ALS, 1 p.
    Sends writing to clarify his viewpoint; mentions "Man and Romance."
  - Theodore Dreiser, New York, to [Frank] Harris 1918 Jul 10, ALS, 2 p.
    Finds his piece impressive; sends "Personality," which may have a place in his magazine.
  - Theodore Dreiser, New York, to Willard Dillman, Minneapolis 1918 Aug 29, ALS, 3 p., w/env.
    Offers to pay bulk of expenses to make September 15 trip possible; feels tied down with long promised work; writes that he has looked for an artist to join them on the trip.
  - Theodore Dreiser, New York, to Henry Eastman Lower, Washington 1918 Nov 13, ALS, 1 p., w/env.
    Suggests he paste this letter in his book and send book for Dreiser to autograph; includes copies of Life Art and America in an upcoming volume of essays and has no copies of it.
  - Theodore Dreiser, New York, to Albert Mordell, Philadelphia 1919 Feb 25, ALS, 1 p., w/env.
    Tells him to write Rusy and start a discussion without mentioning Dreiser.
  - Theodore Dreiser, New York, to [Eva] Jacoby, Hurleyville, New York 1919 Jun 8, ALS, 3 p.